so
bante I have some problems in regard to
relationships in my daily life now that
I have been keeping the
precepts it seems to
be affecting those
relationships because other people in my
life don't keep those
precepts and I keep them so now my
family and my friends are all not
keeping the precepts mhm thus we are
live we're going in opposite
directions and it seems that you know so
now they upset with me for keeping the
precepts because I'm doing that which is
going opposite to what they are
doing should
I be trying to get them on my
side or just let them go their own way
as far as I can see those relationships
are not are no longer valuable well yeah
I mean the relationship the
relationships might not be valuable but
you might still be stuck with those
people so you can't just switch switch
it off like if it's the same household
or something like that so you don't have
to change their ways that's not on
you uh but you do need to draw a
line so if if your friends or family
people in your environment are trying to
pressure you to not keep the precepts
means they don't really well they're not
showing respect to your basic choice so
you will need to draw a line just so
they realize that that you know they
might not be showing the respect because
they don't take you
seriously in uh so if you want to be
taken seriously you need to stick to the
precepts and stick to the practice and
put up with the initial peer pressure
and whatever teasing or people being
upset just take that as a result of your
precepts either way you can't you know
you shouldn't be getting angry or trying
to change their ways or get them to
understand you or
something uh sooner or later when people
see that you are not that it's not just
a whim that it's not just some sort of
uh um a momentary inspiration but you
are sticking to it they'll start to
respect it and if they don't then yeah you draw
it and if they don't then yeah you draw
a line and and you tell them and uh you
could have a normal conv ation without
getting angry about it but either way uh
you should not be compromising your
precepts on account of it and you
certainly should not feel like it's your
duty now to change everybody's mind and
get everybody to accept you or something
because that's not going to happen even
if everybody does what everybody thinks
they should be doing people will still
find ways of disagreeing with you and so
on and I was just thinking that's
actually quite common that people you
keep the precepts your family don't keep
the precepts and there might not be
precepts and there might not be
any uh
arguments but there's definitely a there
can be a leaving each
other separation eventually happens and
that's just I mean separation happens
even when neither party keeps the
precepts so this is just like one of the
reasons that yeah so it's it's either
way it's not end of the world really um
it's um especially because this is actually
um especially because this is actually
beneficial as opposed to million of
other worldly things you could be doing
that would bring you and your family to
grow apart this is actually beneficial
for you and your family diminishing
greed diversion and
delusion I think lots of people feel
that pressure is and it it's like if my
parents aren't happy with what I'm doing
I'm doing something wrong it's like I'm
yeah yeah because of the the pressure
that they feel they think well
they they
can't the mind is still not mature
enough to accept that feeling of
discomfort as part of the deal until the
Mind grows out of it so by having that
feeling of discomfort they confuse that
oh I must be doing something wrong
because otherwise why do I feel bad well
you feel bad because you're in the
environment that contradicts your new
mode of behavior
that contradicts your old mode of
behavior your own mode of behavior even
if nobody is against you when you start
keeping the precepts you're going to
feel de pressure more you're going to
feel anxiety uh lack of confidence all
of those things because your sense of
confidence and being sure in yourself
was based on worldly things on things
that were uh rooted in greed a verion
illusion and now you're diminishing that
so A sense of self is kind of fading and
and it's not going to be felt pleasantly
so the point is to then realize that
feeling unpleasant does not necessarily
mean you're doing something
wrong it could mean that but obviously
that's when you reflect upon the whole
situation and you see hold on I'm not
doing anything wrong yes I feel bad or
why do I feel bad well because the bad
feeling has arisen on account of keeping
the precepts mind is not in my control
in that fundamental sense it will feel
whatever feeling comes and mine is to
not lo my my job my duty is to not lose
perspective regarding that perspective in like in
regarding that perspective in like in
what what you should continue to be
doing which is keep the precepts and not
giving to the pressure of your
feeling and if people are not clear on
that level that's when they they give in
like no amount of peers can pressure
you unless you're already pressuring
yourself unless you're already giving
into that pressure unless you're
uncertain whether you can give in or
not but if you know that you would
wouldn't be breaking the precepts no no
amount of your friends or family can
make you do so well if you know what is
wholesome and what is not yeah
eventually you get to obviously
understand on a deeper level wholesome
is wholesome UNH wholesome is UN
wholesome but initially it would just
come out of reasoning but even such as
such it's it's a valid valid position to
take yeah it is UNH wholesome it is
distracting it is
detrimental unb beneficial I won't do it
and I'll stick to it
and now other people might tease you or
not see you in the same way well that's
part of the deal but what are you taking
as your guide your your parents or the
Dumber you know that that perspective of
this is wholesome this is UNH wholesome
well what they're taking is their guide
is their feeling yeah if they give into
the pressure it's it's they're acting
out of their feeling because they don't
want to Bear it so they compromise their
perspective